And then, the day came.
We had been talking about it for weeks.
We used to live in a colony of thirty families, on the bank of the Volta river.
When I think about home, I think of a joyous crowd.
I grew up surrounded by the constant chatter of my uncles and aunts.
They used to pester us. The useless youth, they called us, eating, chittering and sunbathing on the riverbanks instead of getting ready.
“When I was your age”, my aunt Afefa said, “I was already on my way to Europe!”
What she didn’t know is, this was our way of getting ready.
As sand martins, it is our number that gives us strength.
How else would you expect a 14g bird to travel across 5000 kilometres? It’s madness, when you think about it.
So we chatted to boost our confidence, bragging about who would be the first to cross the desert, who would fly the highest, the fastest.
We chatted to forget how terrified we were.
Because we knew the odds, we knew them all too well. Three out of four of us would never see Europe.
We couldn’t help looking at each other, wondering who it would be.
So we made it last. We made provisions of sun, of sounds, of smells. We boosted our bodies and souls. We became stronger, as a team.
Because we knew that, as much as we would miss home, we simply had no choice. We had to go.